Preliminary Inventory to the Charles Beach Boothe Papers, 1850-1976
Hoover Institution Archives
Charles Beach Boothe Papers,
1850-1976
65006
Boothe, Charles Beach, 1851-1913
3 manuscript boxes (1.2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, memoranda, and clippings, relating to the involvement of C. B. Boothe, Homer Lea, and other Americans, with Sun Yat-sen and other Chinese, in schemes to overthrow the Chinese Imperial Government, 1908-1911, and to Laurence Boothe, son of C. B. Boothe, 1905-1976. Includes a mounted photograph of Sun Yat-sen, 1910; printed copies of two books by Homer Lea, The Vermilion Pencil, and The Valor of Ignorance; and photocopies of mortality registers of Sacramento, California, 1850-1851.
Administrative Information
Access
Box 1 (containing fragile original materials) closed. Use photocopies of these materials are located in Box 2.
Access Points
Lea, Homer, 1876-1912.; Sun, Yat-sen, 1866-1925; Americans--China.; China.; China--History--Hsuan-t'ung, 1908-1912.; United States--Foreign relations.
Container List
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1908-1911 (Box 1-2)
  Holograph and typescript correspondence and telegrams, including some carbon copies, relating to a plot to overthrow the Imperial Chinese Government. The originals, located in Box 1, are restricted; the photocopies in Box 2 are available for research use.
  - Correspondence between C. B. Boothe and Dr. Yung Wing (Folder 1: 1)
    - Oct. 9, 1908. Wing to Boothe. 2 p., ms. /Small double sheet./, 1
    - Oct. 21, 1908. Wing to Boothe. 3 p., ms. /Small double sheet./, 2
    - Dec. 5, 1908. Wing to Boothe and Homer Lea. 4 p., ms. /Small double sheet., 3
    - Dec. 6, 1908. Wing to Boothe. 4 p., ms. /Two small double sheets./, 4
    - Dec. 14, 1908. Wing to Boothe. 3 p., typed. /On three sheets of stationery of the Rotary File and Machine Co., Brooklyn, N. Y./, 5
    - Dec. 28, 1908. Boothe to Wing. 3 p., typed, carbon copy. /Three sheets./, 6
    - Jan. 4, 1909. Wing to Boothe. 2 p., ms. /Large double sheet./, 7
    - Jan. 16, 1909. Wing to Boothe and Homer Lea. 6 p., ms. /Three small double sheets./, 8
    - Jan. 16, 1909. Boothe to Wing. 2 p., typed, carbon copy. /One large sheet./, 9
    - Jan. 25, 1909. Wing to Boothe. 4 p., ms. /Four large sheets./, 10
    - Feb. 2, 1909. Boothe to Wing. 1 p., typed, carbon copy. /Large sheet./, 11
    - Feb. 13, 1909. Boothe to Wing. 1 p., typed, carbon copy. /Large sheet./, 12
    - Feb. 19, 1909. Wing to Boothe. 5 p., ms. /Five large sheets./, 13
    - Feb. 22, 1909. Wing to Boothe. 2 p., ms., and post-script: 1 p., ms. /Two large sheets, and small double sheet./, 14
    - Mar. 6, 1909. Boothe to Wing, with post-script. 2 p., typed, carbon copy; post-script: 1 p., ms. /Large sheet; and small double sheet./, 15
    - June 5, 1909. Wing to Boothe. 2 p., ms. /Large double sheet./, 16
    - June 11, 1909. Boothe to Wing. 2 p., typed, carbon copy. /One sheet./, 17
    - Sept. 14, 1909. Wing to Boothe. 4 p., ms. /Small double sheet./, 18
    - Oct. 2, 1909. Boothe to Wing. 3 p., typed, carbon copy. /Two large sheets./, 19
    - Oct. 20, 1909. Wing to Boothe. 4 p., ms. /Small double sheet./, 20
    - Dec. 23, 1909. Boothe to Wing. 2 p., typed, carbon copy. /Large sheet./, 21
    - Mar. 4, 1910. Wing to Boothe and Homer Lea, with enclosure: copy of letter from Wing to Sun Yat Sen dated Feb. 16, 1910.. Letter to Boothe and Lea: 2 p., ms. /Large double sheet./ Enclosure: 2 p., ms., copy. /On two very flimsy sheets of paper, damaged./, 22
    - Mar. 16, 1910. Wing to Boothe. 2 p., ms. /Large double sheet./, 23
    - Mar. 28, 1910. Wing to Boothe, with enclosure A plan to negotiate a loan. 1 p., ms. /Large sheet/ Enclosure: 4 p., ms. /Four large sheets./, 24
    - May 26, 1910. Wing to Boothe. 2 p., ms. /Small double sheet./, 25
    - Nov. 10, 1910. Wing to Mr. and Mrs. Boothe. 2 p., ms. /Large double sheet./, 26
  - Correspondence between C. B. Boothe and W. W. Allen (Folder 1: 2)
    - Nov. 18, 1908. Boothe to Allen. 2 p., typed, carbon copy. /Two large sheets/, 27
    - Nov. 19, 1908. Allen to Boothe, with enclosure: Century Code Co. circular letter to C. B. Boothe and Co. 2 p., typed. /Two large sheets./ Enclosure: 1 p., typed. /Large sheet./, 28
    - Nov. 25, 1908. Allen to Boothe. 2 p., typed. /Two large sheets., 29
    - Dec. 7, 1908. Allen to Boothe. 2 p., typed. /Two large sheets./, 30
    - Dec. 23, 1908. Boothe to Allen. 1 p., typed, carbon copy. /Large sheet./, 31
    - Dec. 28, 1908. Boothe to Allen. 2 p., typed, carbon copy. /Two large sheets./, 32
    - Jan. 2, 1909. Boothe to Allen. 1 p., typed, carbon copy. /Large sheet./, 33
    - Jan. 4, 1909. Allen to Boothe. 1 p., typed. /Large sheet./, 34
    - Jan. 6, 1909. Allen to Boothe. 1 p., typed. /Large sheet./, 35
      (Letter incorrectly headed Jan. 6, 1908.)
    - Jan. 11, 1909. Allen to Boothe. 1 p., typed. /Large sheet./, 36
    - Jan. 12, 1909. Allen to Boothe. 1 p., typed. /Large sheet./, 37
      (Enclosure mentioned but not found here.)
    - Jan. 21, 1909. Allen to Boothe. 2 p., typed. /Two large sheets./, 38
    - Jan. 25, 1909. Boothe to Allen. 2 p., typed, carbon copy. /Large sheet./, 39
    - Jan. 29, 1909. Allen to Boothe. 3 p., typed. /Three large sheets./, 40
      (Newspaper column 1 long glued to first sheet.)
    - Feb. 1, 1909. Allen to Boothe. 2 p., typed. /Two large sheets./, 41
    - Feb. 3, 1909. Boothe to Allen with enclosures: Officials in sequence and Principal Reform Societies. 2 p., typed, carbon copy. /Large sheet./ Enclosures: 2 p., typed, carbon copies. /Two large sheets./, 42
    - Feb. 3, 1909. Boothe to Allen. 3 p., typed, carbon copy. /Two large sheets./, 43
    - Feb. 6, 1909. Allen to Boothe. 5 p., ms. /Five long sheets/, 44
    - Feb. 6, 1909. Allen to Boothe. 1 p., ms. /Large sheet./, 45
    - Feb. 10, 1909. Allen to Boothe. 1 p., typed. /Large sheet./, 46
      (Enclosure mentioned not found here.)
    - Feb. 11, 1909. Allen to Boothe. 1 p., ms. /Small double sheet./, 47
    - Feb. 12, 1909. Boothe to Allen. 2 p., typed, carbon copy. /Large sheet./, 48
    - Feb. 13, 1909. Allen to Boothe. 2 p., typed. /Two large sheets./, 49
    - Mar. 1, 1909. Allen to Boothe. 1 p., typed. /One large sheet./, 50
      (Clippings mentioned not enclosed here.)
    - Mar. 19, 1909. Allen to Boothe. 1 p., typed. /One large sheet./, 51
      (Enclosed clippings not found here.)
    - Mar. 14, 1910. Allen to Boothe. 2 p., typed. /Two large sheets./, 52
    - Mar. 31, 1910. Allen to Boothe. 3 p., typed. /Three large sheets./, 53
    - Apr. 4, 1910. Allen to Boothe. 2 p., ms. /Small double sheet./, 54
    - July 12, 1910. Allen to Boothe. 1 p., night letter, typed. /Small sheet./, 55
    - July 19, 1910. Boothe to Allen. 1 p., typed. /Large sheet./, 56
    - July 23, 1910. Allen to Boothe. 2 p., ms. /Single small sheet./, 57
  - Correspondence between C. B. Boothe and Sun Yat Sen (Folder 1: 3)
    - Mar. 14, 1910. Sun Yat Sen statement concerning appointment of Boothe as foreign financial agent for Fed. Assc. of China. 1 p., typed. /Large sheet./, 58
    - Mar. 21, 1910. Sun Yat Sen to Boothe. 2 p., ms. /Small double sheet./, 59
    - Apr. 5, 1910. Sun Yat Sen to Boothe. 1 p., ms. /Large sheet, Liberty News letterhead./, 60
    - May 12, 1910. Boothe to Sun Yat Sen. 2 p., typed, carbon copy. /Large sheet./, 61
    - May 24, 1910. Sun Yat Sen to Boothe. 1 p., ms. /Large sheet, Liberty News letterhead./, 62
    - June 22, 1910. Sun Yat Sen to Boothe. 2 p., ms. /Two large sheets./, 63
    - June 22, 1910. Sun Yat Sen to Boothe. 1 p., typed, carbon copy. /Large sheet, typed copy of preceding letter./, 64
    - June 25, 1910. Boothe to Sun Yat Sen. 1 p., typed, carbon copy. /Large sheet./, 65
    - July 15, 1910. Sun Yat Sen to Boothe. 2 p., ms., and post-script: 1 p., ms. /Three small sheets./, 66
    - Sept. 4, 1910. Sun Yat Sen to Boothe. 3 p., ms., and post-script: 1/2 p., ms. /Three and 1/2 large sheets./, 67
    - Sept. 26, 1910. Boothe to Sun Yat Sen. 1 p., ms., telegram. /Small sheet./, 68
    - Sept. 26, 1910. Boothe to Sun Yat Sen. 2 p., typed, carbon copy. /Large sheet./, 69
    - Oct. 21, 1910. Boothe to Sun Yat Sen. 1 p., typed, carbon copy. /Large sheet./, 70
    - Nov. 8, 1910. Sun Yat Sen to Boothe. 3 p., ms. /Three small sheets./, 71
    - Dec. 16, 1910. Sun Yat Sen to Boothe. 3 p., ms. /Small double sheet./, 72
    - Mar. 6, 1911. Sun Yat Sen to Boothe. 2 p., ms. /Two small sheets./, 73
    - Apr. 13, 1911. Boothe to Sun Yat Sen. 1 p., typed, carbon copy. /Large sheet./, 74
  - Correspondence between C. B. Boothe and Homer Lea (Folder 1: 4)
    - Apr. 7, 1908. Lea to Boothe. 1 p., typed. /Large sheet./, 75
    - Aug. 26, 1908. Lea to Boothe. 1 p., typed. /Large sheet./, 76
    - Sept. 11, 1908. Boothe to Lea. 1 p., typed, carbon copy. /Large sheet./, 77
    - Sept. 21, 1908. Lea to Boothe. 2 p., typed. /Two large sheets./, 78
    - Oct. 5, 1908. Lea to Boothe. 1 p., typed. /Large sheet./, 79
    - Nov. 17, 1908. Lea to Boothe. 1 p., typed. /Large sheet./, 80
    - June 21, 1910. Lea to Boothe. 1 p., typed night letter. /Small sheet./, 81
    - June 26, 1910. Lea to Boothe. 3 p., ms. /Small double sheet./, 82
    - Sept. 25, 1910. Lea to Boothe. 1 p., typed. /Large sheet./, 83
  - Correspondence between C. B. Boothe and Charles B. Hill (Folder 1: 5)
    - Jan. 12, 1911. Boothe to Hill. 2 p., typed, carbon copy. /Large sheet./, 84
    - Mar. 3, 1911. Hill to Boothe. 2 p., typed. /Two large sheets./, 85
  - Correspondence of C. B. Boothe with various persons (Folder 1: 6)
    - June 14, 1909. Boothe to Kang Yu Wei. 2 p., typed, carbon copy. /Large sheet./, 86
    - June 21, 1910. T. Schneider to Boothe. 1 p., typed, telegram. /Small sheet./, 87
  - Letters of Yung Wing to Homer Lea (Folder 1: 7)
    - Dec. 4, 1908. Wing to Homer Lea. 2 p., ms. /Two large sheets./, 88
  - Letters of Sun Yat Sen to Homer Lea (Folder 1: 8)
    - Feb. 24, 1910. Sun Yat Sen to Lea. 1 p., ms. /Small sheet./, 89
    - April 1910. Sun Yat Sen to Lea. 3 p., typed copy. /Two large sheets./, 90
    - Sept. 5, 1910. Sun Yat Sen to Lea. 3 p., ms.; post-script: 1 p., ms. /Four large sheets./, 91
  - Homer Lea's estimate of a revolution in China and letter to W. W. Allen (Folder 1: 9)
    - Summer 1909. Homer Lea's estimate. 4 p., ms. /Three small sheets, torn./, 92
    - June 13, 1910. Lea to Allen. 1 p., typed. /Large sheet./, 93
- NON-PRINTED DOCUMENTS, 1905-1910 (File 1: 10, 13)
  Miscellaneous documents, including plans, lists, memoranda, financial proposals, letters, and an invitation and a declaration signed by Dr. Sun Yat-sen, relating to a plot to overthrow the Imperial Chinese Government.
  - Miscellaneous documents (Folder 1: 10)
    - no date. Yung Wing to heads of 4 Chinese political associations. 2 p., ms. Copy: 2 p., typed, carbon copy. /Large double sheet; copy: two large sheets./, 94
    - no date. List of influential personalities in China. 2 p., typed. /Two large sheets./, 95
    - Jan. 21, 1909. A plan for the financing of the revolution in China. 2 p., typed, carbon copy. Memorandum of proposal, 1 p., typed /Three large sheets./, 96
    - Jan. 27, 1909. Revision No. 1 of the plan. 2 p., typed, carbon copy. Wants of China: 1 p., typed, carbon copy. /Three legal sheets./, 97
    - Feb. 1, 1909. List of important Chinese, secret societies, foreign representatives in the U. S., U. S. representatives abroad, Governmental organization, provinces, seaports. 8 p., typed, carbon copy. /Eight legal sheets./, 98
    - Mar., 12, 1910. Detailed plan on revolutionary forces within China, proposals for financial support of the revolution. 3 p., typed, carbon copy. /Three large sheets./, 99
    - Mar. 14, 1910. Memoranda on payments to carry out revolution in China. 4 p., typed, carbon copy. /Four large sheets./, 100
- PRINTED MATERIALS, 1908-1966.
  Clippings and printed articles relating to the plot to overthrow the Imperial Chinese Government.
  - Newspaper clippings (Folder 1: 11)
    - Jan. 24, 1909. N. Y. Daily Herald article concerning negotiations between Tang Shao Yi and J. P. Morgan, others. /8 1/2 column./, 101
    - Dec. 17, 1909. Times Literary Supplement article, The Mastery of the Pacific. /1/2 page./, 102
    - no date. Article, 'General' Homer Lea. /8 clipping, 2 columns wide., 103
    - dateline Nov. 16. Article, S. S.S.? Cruiser Cincinnati leaves Vallejo for China. /10 1/2, 2 columns wide./, 104
  - Miscellaneous materials on Sun Yat Sen, Yung Wing, and on the Boothe Papers (Folder 1: 12)
    - Jan. 28, 1912. Article, American Christian, President of China. Photostat reproduction of one full page of Times-Democrat., 105
    - August 1965. Article, Yung Wing in America. Reprint from Pacific Historical Review, Vol. XXXIV, No. 3, p. 265-87. /Twelve sheets./, 106
    - Oct. 13, 1966. Article, Americans' plot for Chinese revolt revealed. Los Angeles Times reprint. 6 p. /Large double sheet, one insert./, 107
  - Photocopies of items in Box 1; photocopies only available for research use. (Box 2, Folder 1-13)
  - Lea, Homer. Books (Box 3)
    - The Vermillion Pencil, 1908 (Folder 1)
    - The Valor of Ignorance, 1909
- MISCELLANY, 1850-1973 (Box 3)
  Printed article, clipping, envelopes, notes and a duplicate copy of the letters previously described; correspondence and two photocopies of a mortality register kept by Earl S. Youman, an undertaker in Sacramento, California (grandfather of the donor, Mr. Laurence Boothe); and correspondence and miscellany relating to a trip to Taiwan by Mr. Laurence Boothe (includes correspondence with Sun Fo, son of Dr. Sun Yat-sen).
  - General. Clipping, letter, envelopes, photocopies of letters, and a printed article about Homer Lea (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Sun, Fo. Primarily correspondence and miscellany relating to a trip to Taiwan by Mr. Laurence Boothe, 1966-1973 (Folder 3)
  - California Historical Society, 1850-1966. Correspondence and two photocopies of a mortality register kept by Earl S. Youman, an undertaker in Sacramento, California (grandfather of the donor, Mr. Laurence Boothe) (Folder 4)
- AUDIOVISUAL FILE, 1910. (Box 10.A-V)
  - One photograph of Dr. Sun Yat-sen and his son, Sun Fo, taken in Honolulu, and inscribed, 1910 (Folder A)